Department of Justice Investigative Files on Industrial Workers of the World, Part 1 on Microfilm 5863 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- RG 60 - Straight Numerical File (Reel 7)
  - 0229. Industrial Workers of the World - By States - Enclosures. Enclosures to Case File 186701. Section 49. Washington. 16 pages., 1917- 1921; 34 (Reel 7)
    People: L. J. Baley; George F. Vanderveer; J. Edgar Hoover; Alfred Bettman; A. B. Bielaski; William C. Fitts. Subjects: Military Intelligence Division cooperation with Bureau of Intelligence; list of Industrial Workers of the World organizers in New Mexico, Colorado, Texas, Arizona, and Idaho; Bureau of Investigation surveillance of Industrial Workers of the World activities in Washington and Montana; Industrial Workers of the World publications; Italian immigrants; Industrial Workers of the World strike plans; antiwar activities; citizen protests against Industrial Workers of the World activities among lumber workers; travel of Industrial Workers of the World members and hoboes on freight trains.
  - 0245. Industrial Workers of the World - By States - Enclosures. Enclosures to Case File 186701. Section 51. Wisconsin. 1 page., 1917; 35 (Reel 7)
    People: William C. Fitts; A. B. Bielaski. Subject: Antiwar propaganda in Milwaukee, Wisconsin.
  - 0246. Industrial Workers of the World - Subjects - Enclosures. Enclosures to Case File 186701. Section 54. Frank Little matter. 2 pages., 1921; 36 (Reel 7)
    People: Frank Little. Subject: Cover letters to photographs of body and warning placed on body after lynching of Industrial Workers of the World executive board member Frank Little in Butte, Montana.
  - 0248. Industrial Workers of the World - Subjects - Enclosures. Enclosures to Case File 186701. Section 74, Part 1. Centralia and Seattle, Washington, Industrial Workers of the World cases. 2 pages., 1919; 37 (Reel 7)
    People: J. Edgar Hoover. Subjects: Espionage Act prosecutions; United States congressman protests against Department of Justice prosecution of editors of the Seattle Union Record.
  - 0250. Industrial Workers of the World - Subjects - Enclosures. Enclosures to Case File 186701. Section 74, Part 2. Centralia and Seattle, Washington, Industrial Workers of the World cases. 1 page., 1920; 38 (Reel 7)
    People: Alanson Sessions. Subject: Bureau of Investigations memorandum regarding identity of Seattle Union Record editor Alanson Sessions.
  - 0251. Industrial Workers of the World - Subjects - Enclosures. Enclosures to Case File 186701. Section 03. Nicholas Radivoeff. 36 pages., 1920; 39 (Reel 7)
    People: Nicholas Radivoeff; T.F. Nolan; A.S. Embree. Subjects: Transcript of hearing of United States Department of Labor Immigration Service held in Butte, Montana, in the case of Nicholas Radivoeff and Adolphus Stewart Embree; testimony of Bureau of Investigation special agent in case; deportations; immigrant labor; Industrial Workers of the World publications; private detective agencies; Department of Justice surveillance of Industrial Workers of the World activities in Montana and Idaho.
  - 0287. Industrial Workers of the World - Subjects - Enclosures. Enclosures to Case File 186701. Section 266, Special Section Bureau Papers Only. Industrial Workers of the World Situation, San Francisco District. 86 pages., 1921; 40 (Reel 7)
    People: Simon J. Lubin; J. Vance Thompson; Frederick H. Esmond. Subjects: Bureau of Investigation reports on surveillance of Industrial Workers of the World activities in San Francisco, California; Marine Transport Workers Union; California state criminal syndicalism laws and raids on Industrial Workers of the World union offices; Industrial Workers of the World organization and publications; California District Defense Committee of the Industrial Workers of the World; fund raising and legal defense efforts; strike plans of Oil Workers Industrial Union in California; mass meetings; United Communist party publications.
  - 0373. Industrial Workers of the World - Subjects - Enclosures. Enclosures to Case File 186701. Section 361. Werner Kauffeldt. 6 pages., 1923- 1930; 41 (Reel 7)
    People: Werner Kauffeldt; Anna Lipton; J. Edgar Hoover. Subjects: Informant's reports to the Bureau of Investigation on Industrial Workers of the World activities and sabotage plans of Anna Lipton in New York City; Marine Transport Workers Union in Maryland.
  - 0380. Bisbee, Arizona, Deportations. Case File 186813. Section 1. 355 pages., 1917-1918; 42 (Reel 7)
    People: George W. P. Hunt; Thomas A. Flynn; William C. Fitts; John Lord O'Brian; Thomas W. Gregory; Joseph P. Tumulty; John W. Davis; Samuel Gompers; William B. Wilson; Woodrow W. Wilson; Frank K. Nebeker; Thomas E. Campbell; Harry C. Wheeler; Louis F. Post; A. B. Bielaski; A.S. Embree; William C. Redfield; Charles Warren; Grover H. Perry; Irwin St. John Tucker; S. Burkhart; Abner E. Woodruff; Joseph Cannon; George L. Bell; Emmett D. Boyle; Walter S. Gifford. Subjects: Industrial disputes at copper mines in globe and Miami, Arizona; Industrial Workers of the World organization and strike plans of mine workers in Arizona; Globe, Arizona, Home Guards; deployment of federal troops in Arizona; United States War Department cooperation with Department of Justice; Department of Justice prosecution plans and draft indictment of vigilantes and local officials involved in Bisbee, Arizona, deportations of Industrial Workers of the World members; citizen and United States congressman protests against Industrial Workers of the World activities among lumber workers in Arizona; summary of state laws regarding kidnapping; citizen and union protests against deportations of Industrial Workers of the World members from Bisbee, Arizona; United States Department of Labor interest in case; President's Mediation Commission; Loyalty League of America, Bisbee, Arizona; executive committee Bisbee Deportees; immigrant labor; United States War Department list and histories of Bisbee, Arizona, Industrial Workers of the World deportees held in Columbus, New Mexico; minutes of conference of Thomas E. Campbell, governor of Arizona, with Citizens' Committee of Bisbee, Arizona; lynching of Industrial Workers of the World executive board member Frank Little in Butte, Montana; finances of Industrial Workers of the World local union in Bisbee, Arizona; Socialist party of America; Industrial Workers of the World publications; private detective agencies; California Commission on Immigration and Housing; plan of governors of Western states for dealing with labor problems and Industrial Workers of the World activities; National Defense Council. Frames 0735-0872 are a partial duplication of Section 1.
  - 0873. Bisbee, Arizona, Deportations. Case File 186813. Section 2. 252 pages., 1918-1924; 43 (Reel 7)
    People: Thomas A. Flynn; Harry M. Daugherty; Walter Nelles; A. Mitchell Palmer; Harry C. Wheeler; Charles Evans Hughes; Alexander C. King; Wiley E. Jones; Claude R. Porter; William C. Fitts; Thomas W. Gregory; George W. P. Hunt; William C. Herron; Thomas E. Campbell. Subjects: Citizen protests against Industrial Workers of the World activities in Arizona; vigilantes; Department of Justice prosecution of vigilantes and local officials involved in Bisbee, Arizona, deportations of Industrial Workers of the World members; President's Mediation Commission; union and citizen protests against Bisbee, Arizona, deportations of Industrial Workers of the World members; general strikes in Jerome, globe, and Miami, Arizona; Phelps-Dodge Corporation purchase of firearms used in Bisbee deportations; indictment and reply brief in case against Harry C. Wheeler, et al.; deployment of United States troops in Arizona mining centers.
  - 1125. Bisbee, Arizona, Deportations. Case File 186813. Section 2. Previously Restricted Materials. 12 pages., 1918; 44 (Reel 7)
    People: A. B. Bielaski; William C. Fitts. Subjects: Bureau of Investigation report on conditions in Bisbee, Arizona, prior to deportations of Industrial Workers of the World members; strikes; vigilantes; United States Post Office Department censorship of Industrial Workers of the World mail.
- RG 60 - Straight Numerical File (Reel 8)
  - 0001. William D. Haywood. Case File 188032. Section 1, Part 1. 199 pages., 1917-1918; 1 (Reel 8)
    People: William D. Haywood; William C. Fitts; Frank K. Meeker; Claude R. Porter; Thomas W. Gregory; Charles Page; Josephus Daniels; Charles F. Clyne; John Lord O'Brian; Roger N. Baldwin; Elizabeth Gurley Flynn; Arturo Giovannitti; Carlo Tresca; Joseph Graber; Adolph Germer; Joseph J. Ettor; Kenesaw M. Landis; Clarence L. Reames; Grover H. Perry; Samuel Block; John L. Metzen; Charles Warren; Stanley J. Clark; Hinton Clabaugh. Subjects: Department of Justice Chicago, Illinois, prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World leadership and Industrial Workers of the World members; United States Shipping Board; United States Navy Department; United States War Department; National Civil Liberties Bureau; arrest of Industrial Workers of the World defendants in case; Industrial Workers of the World publications; citizen and United States congressman protests against Industrial Workers of the World activities; General Defense Committee of the Industrial Workers of the World; Department of Justice raids on Industrial Workers of the World offices and seizure of Industrial Workers of the World documents; citizen protests against Department of Justice prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World members and leadership list of defendants in case; draft indictment in case against William D. Haywood, et al.
  - 0200. William D. Haywood. Case File 188032. Section 1, Part 2. 233 pages., 1918-1919; 2 (Reel 8)
    People: William D. Haywood; Alexander C. King; Elizabeth Gurley Flynn; Arturo Giovannitti; Carlo Tresca; Claude R. Porter; Charles F. Clyne; George F. Vanderveer; E.T. Doran; A.S. Embree; Benjamin H. Fletcher; Jacob Friedrich; Charles Recht; Francis G. Caffey; Thomas W. Gregory; Learned Hand; Frank K. Nebeker; John Lind; William C. Herron; George N. Murdock; William C. Fitts; Ralph M. Easley. Subjects: Department of Justice policies regarding the bail and parole of Industrial Workers of the World defendants; Department of Justice Chicago, Illinois, prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World leadership and Industrial Workers of the World members; Department of Justice seizure of Industrial Workers of the World documents; General Defense Committee of the Industrial Workers of the World; surveillance of mails of Industrial Workers of the World members and Industrial Workers of the World lawyers; United States Post Office Department cooperation with Department of Justice; American Protective League surveillance of Industrial Workers of the World mailing procedures. Dates in Section 1, Part 2 correspond with those that would fall in Section 3 and so are presumed to be a misfile of Section 3.
  - 0433. William D. Haywood. Case File 188032. Section 1. Previously Restricted Materials. 32 pages., 1917; 3 (Reel 8)
    People: William D. Haywood; Thomas W. Gregory; Frank K. Nebeker; Carlton H. Parker; George F. Vanderveer; William C. Fitts; Hinton Clabaugh; A.B. Bielaski; Fred Hardy; Stanley J. Clark. Subjects: Department of Justice Chicago, Illinois prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World leadership and Industrial Workers of the World members; Industrial Workers of the World fund raising and legal defense efforts; suggested methods of arranging Industrial Workers of the World evidence in case against William D. Haywood, et al.; Department of Justice wartime censorship of publications; sedition and Espionage Act prosecutions; list of potential Industrial Workers of the World detainees in the United States.
  - 0465. William D. Haywood. Case File 188032. Section 2. 396 pages., 1918; 4 (Reel 8)
    People: William D. Haywood; William C. Fitts; Frank K. Nebeker; Claude R. Porter; Thomas W. Gregory; Kenesaw M. Landis; Newton D. Baker; Richard T. Ely; A.B. Bielaski; Charles F. Clyne; J. Robert O'Connor; Clarence L. Reames; George Andreytchine; Joseph J. Ettor; George N. Murdock; W. H. Lamar; Francis G. Caffey; John P. Feeny; George Hardy; Josephus Daniels; Joseph P. Tumulty; George F. Vanderveer; Roger N. Baldwin; Ralph M. Easley; George Creel; William B. Wilson; Elizabeth Gurley Flynn; Carlo Tresca; Arturo Giovannitti; Woodrow W. Wilson; George P. West. Subjects: Department of Justice Chicago, Illinois, prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World leadership and Industrial Workers of the World members; citizen protests against Industrial Workers of the World activities and against Department of Justice prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World members; Industrial Workers of the World publications; United States War Department and United States Navy Department cooperation with department of Justice; Espionage Act prosecutions; answer to petition for return of papers and petition for impounding order in case against William D. Haywood, et al.; affidavit as to documents seized by Department of Justice and lists of Industrial Workers of the World documents and publications in storage in case against William D. Haywood, et al.; United States Post Office Department cooperation with Department of Justice in censorship of Industrial Workers of the World publications; General Defense Committee of the Industrial Workers of the World; League for National Unity.
  - 0861. William D. Haywood. Case File 188032. Section 2. Enclosures. 12 pages., 1918; 5 (Reel 8)
    People: William d. Haywood; William C. Fitts. Subjects: Department of Justice Chicago, Illinois, prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World leadership and Industrial Workers of the World members; special report regarding Industrial Workers of the World activities in Portland, Oregon; Industrial Workers of the World union organization; Espionage Act Prosecutions; Soviet Russian consulate in Seattle, Washington.
  - 0873. William D. Haywood. Case File 188032. Section 4. 263 pages., 1918-1919; 6 (Reel 8)
    People: William D. Haywood; Charles F. Clyne; A. Mitchell Palmer; Claude R. Porter; Vincent St. John; Clarence Darrow; Raymond S. Fanning; George N. Murdock; Kenesaw M. Landis; George F. Vanderveer; Frank K. Nebeker; Francis G. Caffey; Harry Weinberger; George Andreytchine; John Lord O'Brian; Alexander C. King; David S. Cook; Louis F. Post; Charles Recht; Arturo Giovannitti; Alexander S. Lanier; Charles Ashleigh; Herman Richter; George W. Whiteside; Elizabeth Gurley Flynn; Carlo Tresca; Thomas W. Gregory; Alfred Bettman. Subjects: Department of Justice Chicago, Illinois, prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World leadership and Industrial Workers of the World members; citizen protests against Industrial Workers of the World activities and against Department of Justice prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World members; Industrial Workers of the World organization of black Americans; list of defendants released on bond; charge of Judge Landis to the jury in case against William D. Haywood, et al.; Department of Justice policies regarding bail and parole for Industrial Workers of the World defendants; United States War Department cooperation with Department of Justice; plans for disposition of Industrial Workers of the World documents and property seized by the department of Justice.
  - 1136. William D. Haywood. Case File 188032. Section 5. 248 pages., 1919-1920; 7 (Reel 8)
    People: William D. Haywood; Charles F. Clyne; David S. Cook; Robert P. Stewart; Frank K. Nebeker; A. Mitchell Palmer; George Andreytchine; Louis F. Post; Claude R. Porter; John L. Metzen. Subjects: Department of Justice Chicago, Illinois, prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World leadership and Industrial Workers of the World members; citizen and United States congressman protests against Industrial Workers of the World activities; Industrial Workers of the World publications; General Defense Committee of the Industrial Workers of the World; International Workers' Defense League; Department of Justice policies regarding bail and parole for Industrial Workers of the World defendants; plans for disposition of Industrial Workers of the World documents and property seized by the Department of Justice.
- RG 60 - Straight Numerical File (Reel 9)
  - 0000. William D. Haywood. Case File 188032. Section 5. Previously Restricted Materials and Enclosures. 24 pages., 1918-1919; 1 (Reel 9)
    People: William D. Haywood; Frank K. Nebeker; J. Edgar Hoover; Charles H. McKinnon; A. Mitchell Palmer; Benjamin H. Fletcher; A.B. Bielaski; George N. Murdock. Subjects: Department of Justice Chicago, Illinois, prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World leadership and Industrial Workers of the World members; plans for disposition of documents and property seized by the Department of Justice; Industrial Workers of the World publications; citizen and United States congressman protests against Industrial Workers of the World activities; private detective agencies; United States Post Office Department censorship of Industrial Workers of the World mail.
  - 0024. William D. Haywood. Case File 188032. Section 6. 213 pages., 1920-1938; 2 (Reel 9)
    People: William D. Haywood; Arturo Giovannitti; J. Edgar Hoover; Homer S. Cummings; Joseph B. Fleming; Victor L. Berger; Forrest Edwards; Vincent St. John; Raymond S. Fanning; A. Mitchell Palmer; William L. Frierson; Francis Ralston Welsh; James H. Rowan; Louis F. Post; Frank K. Nebeker; David S. Cook. Subjects: Department of Justice Chicago, Illinois, prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World leadership and Industrial Workers of the World members; requests for access to Department of Justice files on case against William D. Haywood, et al.; Department of Justice request for United States Department of State verification of death of William D. Haywood in Russia; application for writ of certiorari before the United States Supreme Court; United States Circuit Court of Appeals hearings; surveillance of mail of prisoners in Leavenworth, Kansas, penitentiary; General Defense Committee of the Industrial Workers of the World; Department of Justice policies regarding parole and bail for Industrial Workers of the World defendants; Industrial Workers of the World fund raising, legal defense, and organization of agricultural workers in South Dakota; citizen protests against Industrial Workers of the World activities and against Department of Justice prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World members; Industrial Workers of the World publications; plans for disposition of Industrial Workers of the World documents and property seized by the Department of Justice.
  - 0237. William D. Haywood. Case File 188032. Section 7. 205 pages., 1921-1954; 3 (Reel 9)
    People: William D. Haywood; William C. Fitts; Frank K. Nebeker; Thomas J.D. Salter; Samuel Gompers; J. Edgar Hoover; Harry M. Daugherty; Charles Moyer; Mabel Walker Willebrandt; Ralph Chaplin; Roger N. Baldwin; James A. Finch; Sara B. Field; Ida Palmer; E. F. Doree; Stanley J. Clark; Alexander S. Lanier; Rose Weiss; Harry Weinberger; Charles Ashleigh; Vincent St. John; Charles F. Clyne; John Pancner; Caroline A. Lowe; Robert P. Stewart; Joseph B. Fleming; Annette Abbott Adams. Subjects: Department of Justice Chicago, Illinois, prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World leadership and Industrial Workers of the World members; requests for access to Department of Justice files on case against William D. Haywood, et al; plans for disposition of Industrial Workers of the World documents seized by the Department of Justice; decision of United States Circuit Court of Appeals in case against William D. Haywood, et al.; dismissal of cases against remaining defendants; surveillance of mail of prisoners in Leavenworth, Kansas, penitentiary; General Defense Committee of the Industrial Workers of the World; American Civil Liberties Union; forfeiture of bond by William D. Haywood; interview from Pravda given by William D. Haywood in Moscow regarding the present condition of the labor classes in the United States; United States Supreme Court denial of writ of certiorari in case against William D. Haywood, et al.
  - 0442. William D. Haywood. Case File 188032. Section 6-7. Previously Restricted Materials and Enclosures. 82 pages., 1928-1955; 4 (Reel 9)
    People: William D. Haywood; Herbert McCutcheon; Vincent St. John; William Stanley; J. Edgar Hoover; William C. Fitts; Frank K. Nebeker; Charles F. Clyne. Subjects: Department of Justice Chicago, Illinois, prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World leadership and Industrial Workers of the World members; dismissal of charges against fugitive Industrial Workers of the World defendant Herbert McCutcheon; decision of United States Circuit Court of Appeals in case against William D. Haywood, et al.; investigation of death of William D. Haywood in Moscow, Russia; copy of original indictment in case against William D. Haywood, et al.; attempted extradition of conspiracy defendants from Canada.
  - 0524. William D. Haywood. Case File 188032. Special Section. 20 pages., 1917-1918; 5 (Reel 9)
    People: William D. Haywood; William C. Fitts; Thomas W. Gregory; George F. Vanderveer; George Creel; Frank K. Nebeker; Lincoln Steffens; M. E. Saville. Subjects: Department of Justice Chicago, Illinois, prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World leadership and Industrial Workers of the World members; Committee on Public Information; Industrial Workers of the World activities in the Pacific Northwest; Industrial Workers of the World legal defense efforts.
  - 0544. William D. Haywood. Case File 188032. Special Section. Enclosures and Previously Restricted Materials. 14 pages., 1917-1918; 6 (Reel 9)
    People: William D. Haywood; A. B. Bielaski; Antone Johanson; Frank P. Walsh; George F. Vanderveer; Fred Hardy; Hinton Clabaugh; Roger N. Baldwin; J. A. Wagner. Subjects: Industrial Workers of the World activities in the Pacific Northwest; Industrial Workers of the World legal defense efforts; Office of Naval Intelligence surveillance of mail of Industrial Workers of the World attorneys; Soviet Russian consulate in Seattle, Washington; Civil Liberties Bureau of the American Union against Militarism and the formation of the American Civil Liberties Union or National Civil Liberties Bureau; American visitors to Soviet Russia.
  - 0558. William D. Haywood. Case File 188032. File regarding White E. Gibson, Special Assistant to the Attorney General. 125 pages., 1918; 7 (Reel 9)
    People: William D. Haywood; White E. Gibson; Thomas W. Gregory; Kenesaw M. Landis; William C. Fitts; Frank K. Nebeker; Claude R. Porter; Simon J. Lubin; George F. Vanderveer; George L. Bell; Samuel Gompers; Ralph M. Easley. Subjects: Department of Justice Chicago, Illinois; prosecution of Industrial Workers of the World leadership and Industrial Workers of the World members; Butte, Montana, miners strike and acts of incendiarism at Granite Mountain, Montana; attempts to establish overt acts of sabotage by the Industrial Workers of the World for the prosecution; investigation of Industrial Workers of the World activities on the Pacific Coast; Industrial Workers of the World lumber workers strike and union organization; eight-hour day proposal; National Civic Federation.
  - 0684. F.W. Henshaw. Case File 188044. 66 pages., 1917; 8 (Reel 9)